The future of AI coding is here and my
friend, I mean that most sincerely. Zed
has just introduced the agent client
protocol or ACP for short. It's a
standard just like MCP, but for
connecting any coding assistant to any
code editor. And Zed's integration is
only in beta, but if you want a glimpse
into how we're going to be working with
AI in the near future, this is it. So,
right now, I'll show you ACP in action
and how you can get started with it
yourself right now. Lot of exciting
stuff today. I'll start by showing you
how we can run both cloud code and
Gemini CLI threads in Zed and switch
between them at the click of a button.
And with ACP, we get live updates in our
code editor as the coding assistant is
working. And we can accept and reject
changes, which are things that I've
always wanted in Cloud Code. It makes
the development experience so much
better. And since ACP is a standard,
we're able to create our own custom
agents that we can attach as coding
agents into any editor, just like with
MCP, we're able to build tools that we
can connect into any agent. I'll show
you how that works as well, and even
show you some ideas we're cooking up
along these lines with Archon. So, I'll
be sure to cover how ACP works at a
fundamental level as well. Definitely is
worth understanding this incredible new
technology. So, I first found out about
ACP from this Zed announcement
announcing that they now have support
for Cloud Code. If you don't know, Zed
is a code editor just like VS Code and
its forks like Windsurf and Cursor. And
so, I was really interested how exactly
they integrated with Cloud Code. So, I
clicked into this, read through it, and
it immediately jumped out to me that
they didn't just build a one-off
integration with Cloud Code. They wanted
to build something better and that is
the agent client protocol. The standard
like I said for connecting any coding
agent to any code editor and this is
just such a gamecher. It makes it so
easy to switch between coding
assistants. That's becoming increasingly
important right now as we start to get
more and more options. Cloud code is
becoming less and less of an obvious
winner right now. And so we want to move
between these code editors and try
different ones seamlessly. And that's
what ACP gives us. It's about time that
we have this standard. And more on this
later, it makes it easier for us to run
a lot of code agents in parallel. And
all you have to do to get started with
ACP is install Zed. That's what we're
looking at right here. It's a completely
free and open source code editor. And
I'll have links in the description to
install this depending on your operating
system. And I'm sure in the very near
future, we're going to have a lot of
other code editors like VS Code also
support ACP. But right now, we've got
Zed. And then for coding assistance,
Gemini CLI actually has a direct
integration with ACP. And then Cloud
Code is through an adapter. More on that
later. And I'm sure they're going to be
a lot more coding assistance in the near
future here that will also be supporting
ACP. And once you have it installed,
hooking into the Gemini CLI or Cloud
Code right within Zed could not be
easier. Literally, all you have to do is
open up this agent panel on the right
hand side. So it's just this button in
the bottom right to toggle it on and
off. And then you click on this plus
button right here. And you can start a
new Gemini CLI thread, Claude Code
thread, or any custom agent that you
build, which I'll showcase in a little
bit here. So, for example, let's start a
Gemini CLI thread. It'll load up the
connection to the Gemini CLI. It'll have
you authenticate if it's your first
time, which that is all done right
within the code editor as well. So, it's
super super easy. I can reauthenticate
if I need to. I don't even have to do
any external setup to bring these coding
assistants into my editor because that
is also a part of ACP. It is a beautiful
thing. And so now I can send in a
request here like change the greeting
message in and I can at@mention files
like you would expect to something
random. All of the native features that
we have for these coding assistants work
with zed through ACP as well. So things
like sub agents and custom slash
commands like we have with cloud code,
all of that is still going to work. So
we lose nothing and now we have
everything in this development
environment. So we can see these changes
live in our IDE. We can accept and
reject these things. The kind of stuff
that I've always wanted to have with
Claude code. So I'll reject this one for
now. I don't need it to run this command
because yeah, that's just quick demo of
the Gemini CLI. And then if I want,
boom, there we go. I'm now loaded up a
new thread for Claude code. And I can do
another request like change the goodbye
message to something random. Or I could
build a slash command to do this, right?
And so, yeah, send in this request. It's
going to make an edit just like the
Gemini CLI, but it's using an entirely
different coding assistant, even though
it seems like it isn't because it was
that easy to switch between them. And
there we go. We got the change request
from Cloud Code. Everything looks the
same as Gemini CLI. I can show it looks
like to reject this now. So, I can
reject and give feedback. The kind of
thing that I used to do in Windsurf and
Cursor all of the time that I had to do
more of like a Git integration to revert
stuff with Cloud Code up until this
point. Now, I will say that this
integration definitely feels like it's
in beta in some ways. First of all,
sometimes when I open a new Gemini CLI
thread, it'll hang there trying to load
or connect to the Gemini CLI. Obviously,
it's working right here. I've had that
happen a couple of times. Also, it
appears that the thread history doesn't
work, which is kind of a bummer. So, a
couple of glitches I think that need to
be worked through here. But, I hope that
you can see that this is definitely the
future for AI coding. Just look at how
easy that was to interact with the
coding assistants in my IDE and switch
between them as well. It also is very
much worth understanding how ACP works
fundamentally. I used to say this all
the time for MCP as well. Even if ACP
doesn't end up being the primary
standard adopted for connecting coding
agents to code editors, whatever that
main standard ends up being, it's going
to look a lot like ACP. And I can say
that with confidence because Zed clearly
has a good head on their shoulders with
this implementation. They took a lot of
inspiration from other protocols like
MCP and also the language server
protocol. This is the standard for
connecting programming languages to code
editors. So it's definitely the most
similar protocol. It's been around for
about a decade now. And so they're
building on top of the shoulders of
giants here. Definitely doing it right.
And so I want to focus on ACP here. I'm
not going to dive a ton into leveraging
AI coding assistance in this video or
just focusing on the protocol. I will
say though that if you want to 10x your
AI coding workflow, really take it to
the next level, check out this link that
I'll have on the screen right here. I've
got a really exciting workshop coming up
that you won't want to miss. I'm just
going to leave that golden nugget here.
Definitely check out that site. And with
that, let's go ahead and move on. So, I
will have a link in the description to
this ACP documentation if you really
want to dive into the architecture and
how it works under the hood. I'm just
going to cover kind of the high-level
ideas here just to help you see how
powerful this really is. And so, we've
got our first simple diagram here where
we have our code editor that has a
standard IO. So, just a local connection
to the coding assistance that we have
running. So it spins up an instance of
the Gemini CLI or an instance of cloud
code under the hood that it's connecting
to within Zed and it's very similar to
how MCP works. So like I said, they
definitely are taking inspiration from
these protocols that are working very
very well. And if we go to an overview
of the protocol, this is where they
start to talk about how the
communication works under the hood
between our coding assistants and code
editors. So, it's following a JSON RPC
protocol just like MCP does. And so,
I'll show you a couple examples of what
this looks like. It's actually very
simple because there's just a few set
operations that a coding agent is going
to perform. And so, I'll go to the
prompt turn tab here so you can see what
this looks like. First of all, we create
a session between the client and the
agent. It's kind of like a handshake.
And then just as things are happening
like tool calls or permission requests
or just chunks of text that it needs to
send, these are just going back and
forth between the code editor and the
coding assistant. And so this is an
example of the JSON event for a user
message. So whenever we have a user
enter something into the editor, it's
going to send this JSON event through
ACP to our coding assistant so it can
understand what the user is asking for.
It's going to even include things like
images or resources, calling out
specific files that we want it to edit.
And then when the agent responds, there
are a couple of different responses that
it can give. Like first of all, this is
an example of the JSON that we need our
coding assistant to give through ACP
when it wants to communicate a task list
that it wants to knock out. We see that
all the time with cloud code. Or if it
wants to just send some plain text, it
looks like this. We have a a type of
agent message chunk. Here's the text
that it's going to send through. So, we
can stream that out in our editor. Or if
it wants to make an update to a file or
read a file, those are all done through
agent tool calls. And so, we have a
session update of type tool call. And
then we can give it a title, any other
kind of metadata. Basically, anything
that you would ever see within cloud
code or the Gemini CLI where you can see
the tool call, you can see the file that
it's affecting or the line numbers. All
of that metadata is passed through the
JSON payloads here with ACP. And there's
a couple other things I don't want to
dive super deep into right now.
Definitely check this out if you're
curious and if you want to build your
own custom agents because armed with
this information, we can also start to
play around with the idea of not using
cloud code, not using Gemini CLI, but
actually building our own custom agent.
And they have an example of that in
GitHub as well. The sponsor of today's
video is fly.io, IO, a developer first
cloud platform that makes deploying your
AI Asians, frontends, really any type of
application super straightforward. We're
talking about using AI coding assistance
in this video, and you can build amazing
things with them, but you have to have a
place to deploy to production. And that
is where Fly.io comes in. And what makes
them stand apart is they have their own
infrastructure. They're not just another
AWS wrapper, which means that everything
is going to be cheaper and faster for
you. And you can deploy very easily, no
matter the framework that you use. And
all you have to do to get started with
fly.io is create your account for free
to get started. And then you can install
the CLI so you can work with it on your
computer. And then you log in with the
fly off command. And then take a look at
this. I can go into the directory where
I have my application and run fly
launch. It is going to automatically
recognize the type of my application and
configure things to deploy everything
automatically. There's basically nothing
more that I have to do. It is that easy.
I can customize any configuration that I
want. Otherwise, I just went with the
default values. So, it went ahead and
built the container for my type of
application, deployed to the cloud, and
gave me a domain, which I can customize
later. So, here in the dashboard, we can
see our application. Click into our URL
here, and boom, there we go. We have our
front end deployed on Flat.io's global
infrastructure. And this is actually the
front end that we're building on top of
in the AI coding workshop that I
mentioned earlier. It was that easy to
get everything deployed to production
and fly.io is free to get started. So if
you have those awesome projects that
you've been building with AI coding
assistance and it's time to bring them
to production, this is your platform to
do so. I'd highly recommend checking
them out. Link in the description. So if
we want to build a custom agent using
ACP, we just need to build an
application that follows this
architecture. We use a large language
model under the hood to accept requests
to make code changes and then use tools
to do so and communicate that back out
through ACP. So they have a TypeScript
example in their GitHub repository. I'll
link to this below as well if you want
to check it out. This is what we're
going to test out within Zed right now.
And so they have instructions in this
repo where you can just clone it and
then you add into the configuration in
Zed. I'll show you what that looks like
in a little bit as well. And so clicking
into agent.ts, ts. I'll just show you
how this works really quickly. This
isn't going to be an intelligent
conversation with a real coding agent.
It's just a bunch of hardcoded messages
that are going to be sent through ACP
when we send in a request. So, it's just
kind of a demo that we have here. But
first of all, we have our initialize
function. This is what happens whenever
we make a new connection to the coding
assistant to set things up. And then
when we make a new session or in Z a new
thread, this function is ran. And so
once we are in the prompting mode, this
is where we're going to simulate a turn.
And so this simulate turn function. This
is where you would typically invoke a
large language model and get out the
tool request for it to read certain
files or edit certain files. In this
case, like I said, we just have
hard-coded JSON messages following the
ACP protocol to give these updates to
the frontend. So we send in a request
and then the agent is hardcoded to
communicate through ACP back to our code
editor. I'll help you with that. Let me
start by reading some files to
understand the current situation. And
then it sends a mock tool call saying
that it's going to read a specific file.
And then it does another update here
saying that it is going to replace some
content in a file. So just communicating
some fake tool calls that act like the
agent would act if there was a real
coding agent hooked up here. All right,
so back over in Zed because I followed
the instructions in the GitHub to get my
custom agent installed. And the way that
you get to that configuration, by the
way, is you click on the three dots in
the top right, go to the settings, and
then we can add an external agent like
I've already done here. So, we've got
the Gemini CLI, we've got Cloud Code.
Now, we can add our own. So, it opens up
this JSON right here for you right away
to add in the path to your own custom
agent. Like in this case, this is the
TypeScript file that we have pulled down
from GitHub. So, I'm going to actually
delete this here. I don't need to add
another one, but I can save this. And
then you'll have your external agent
that you can connect to. So going back
here, I can open up a new thread with my
custom agent. And it's nothing fancy
right here. It's just those hardcoded
messages that we saw being passed
through ACP. But just look at how
seamless that was. Like the code was
pretty simple overall in that TypeScript
file. But now we have everything
integrated already with Zed and with any
code editor in the future that works
with ACP. So, it's that easy to build
our own custom agent with all the
different operations that we typically
see with coding assistants. And like I
alluded to earlier, and I promised I
would hit on this more, Cloud Code does
not have a direct integration with ACP.
So, for Zed to add it into their
platform, they had to build an adapter.
And this is simpler than you would
think, thanks to ACP. So, we can look at
the source code here for the adapter.
They have an agent.ts TS just like the
custom agent example that we saw a
little bit ago. And clicking into this,
a lot of the code is going to look very
similar because basically all we have to
do to connect cloud code to any editor
through ACP is we need to convert any of
our cloud code SDK messages into the
format, the JSON format needed for the
ACP standard. And so this function right
here, it takes any cloud code message
and based on the type, like if it's text
or the model is thinking or it's using a
tool to read a file, we're going to take
the output of the cloud code SDK, like
all the different values in these
chunks, and we're going to transform
that into the JSON object necessary for
ACP. So it's really just a data change.
We're just changing the format. That's
all it takes. And so this integration,
this full adapter for cloud code to zed
thanks to ACP is only around 600 lines
of code. It's so simple and we can take
this beautiful notion of this standard
here and apply it to other kinds of
integrations. Like when I saw this, my
mind just started running wild for the
possibilities here with Archon in
particular, my open-source project,
which is the command center for AI
coding assistance. And one of the things
that we've always wanted to build into
it is integrating it with different
coding agents directly. And ACP is
definitely our ticket for that. So I
actually had Raasmus on my team. He did
a proof of concept integrating Archon
with ACP. So yeah, let's take a look at
that right now. It's super super
interesting. All right, so we just took
a look at implementing custom agents
into Zed through ACP. Now, the ability
for us to do this kind of integration
ourselves has just opened up the
floodgate of ideas for me and Raasmus.
So, I brought him in here to show a
proof of concept that he did for Archon
using ACP with Archon to connect it to
Cloud Code and other coding assistants.
And this is very much a PC at this
point, but I just want to share with you
some of the vision that we have here,
some of the ways that we can uh
implement Archon with these coding
agents using ACP. We've always wanted to
do something like what you're about to
see, but ACP just makes it that much
easier because it provides that standard
for connecting applications like Archon
and other code editors to our coding
agents. So, Raasmus, thanks for being
here and building out this proof of
concept. Why don't you share some of
your vision for connecting Archon to
coding agents?
>> Yeah, so yeah, thanks for having me
again. And uh yeah, what you just said
uh our vision has always been to like
have Aron be able to invoke coding
agents, not only cloud code but other
agents like the Gemini CLI or the cursor
agents or even Devon or any any of the
coding agents really. And what ACP will
allow us to do is to do that in one
sweep. So if all of these uh other
agents also adopt this protocol, we will
be able to implement all of them very
very easily and very very quickly as
long as we have our base ACP
implementation.
So, what we have here right now is uh
and yeah, I've been having a blast
building this out with with Archon and
uh here we have uh PC with cloud code,
but we can just as easily use Gemini CLI
because both of them works kind of out
of the box with ACP
and uh this is now directly integrated
into Archon at this PC where you can
basically connect your directory to to
Archon. So the long-term vision here
would be to kind of connect your git
repository to Archon and you can attach
your knowledge base to that git
directory and you can attach your MCP
servers to that git uh directory so that
you can feed all of the context that you
need to feed to your coding agent before
you send your coding agent back uh into
the background to do like a background
task for you. So the agent will kind of
spin up its own work tree, its own
environment where it will can do
whatever it wants and it will come back
to you with a PR uh once it's ready. So
basically you can just uh tell it where
it should work. So I'll just give it a
path to to one of my projects. I can
start a coding session and I can see
this uh uh interface here where I just
have a chat. We have an active session
and uh we can just send it a easy task.
I'm just going to give it an example
task here to create three different
hello world files. One in uh Rust, one
in Go, and one in Python. And uh let's
just kick it off and see what it does.
So we should see the this here what I
have open is actually the HCP back end
that is written in Rust. Uh and yeah,
you can see here that it does it. It's
actually spawns. You can see that it
spawned three sub pages actually and did
it in in one sweep. So yeah, that was
quite an efficient uh task as well. I
can actually open up the files here as
well. And we can see that it all created
this, it created this and this. So yeah,
very simple example but uh quite
powerful uh way of working with coding
agents and I I believe personally that
that's going to be the future way to
work with with coding agents and archon
is our interpretation or will be our
interpretation of of the new interface
for for coding.
>> Exactly right. That is beautiful. Yeah.
And like Razo said, this is just a proof
of concept, not coming anytime soon to
Archon necessarily. And this is a really
basic example, but the power of this is
we are not interacting with cloud code
directly. We're not using the cloud code
SDK, anything like that. It is all
through ACP. That is how we're
communicating here. And so it really
would be a drop in replacement for any
other agent like Gemini CLI that also
supports ACP. That's the beauty of this.
And another thing we can do in Archon is
we can make it very easy to manage many
agents in parallel. all using ACP. So, a
user interface kind of like this, but
being able to click into different
agents as they're active working on
longer running tasks. Something
obviously much longer than the quick
demo here. So, yeah, there's just so
many ways that we can build this out
with Archon.
>> Yeah, exactly that. And imagine an
interface here where you can actually
select your agents. So you can like
select cursor or you can select Gemini
CLI or you can select codeex or whatever
and you can uh send that off you know
and you have a basically a chat that you
can open or close you can inspect what
it's doing or you can ignore it and at
the end of the day it will come back to
you with the with the PR anyways that
you can review at the end. So this is
really a way to to kick this off into
the into the background and do the work
for you. So very similar to what uh uh
the codeex cloud is doing but that you
the difference is that you can do it
with any agent and you you do it locally
on your own machine
>> right yeah it's a beautiful thing so
thank you Raasmus for showing us this
working on the proof of concept the two
big reasons I wanted to put this into
the video here is one to show you some
of the awesome plans we have for Archon
that we've always had but ACP is going
to make easier and then also I hope that
this kind of can enlighten you even more
on what ACP enables and why I really do
think it is the future of AI coding. So,
thanks for being here, Raasmus, and on
to the rest of our video. So, I hope
those ideas around archon really got
your brain juices flowing. There's just
so many ways that ACP really is the
future of AI coding. And also, Raasmus
has a video coming out on his channel
that I'll link to in the description
when it's available. Check that out if
you want to dive even deeper into these
ideas around archon and ACP. So yeah,
that is all the content that I got for
you right now on ACP. It's just an
incredible technology, a standard that
I'm definitely going to be following
more and putting out some more content
as we get more integrations with
different code editors and coding
assistants. So if you appreciate this
video and you're looking forward to more
things AI coding and AI agents, I would
really appreciate a like and a
subscribe. And with that, I will see you
in the next